Guide to the Brooklyn ephemera collection ARC.272
Brooklyn Historical Society
Brooklyn ephemera collection
1814-2001
ARC.272
Brooklyn Historical Society
10.25 linear feet in 12 manuscript boxes, 4 half manuscript boxes, and 2 flat boxes
The Brooklyn ephemera collection contains various ephemeral material relating to a variety of Brooklyn-based institutions and events spanning the period 1814 to 1998.
Box Series 06: Military - 1 of 1
Box Series 05: Entertainment - 2 of 2
Box Series 05: Entertainment - 1 of 2
Box Series 04: Clubs - 2 of 2
Box Series 04: Clubs - 1 of 2
Box Series 03: Civic orgs - 1 of 1
Box Series 02: Churches - 1 of 1
Box Series 01: Business - 1 of 1
Box Series 10: Miscellaneous - 4 of 4
Box Series 10: Miscellaneous - 3 of 4
Box Series 10: Miscellaneous - 2 of 4
Box Series 10: Miscellaneous - 1 of 4
Box Series 09: Transportation - 2 of 2 (flat box)
Box Series 09: Transportation - 1 of 2
Box Series 08: Sports - Box 1 of 1
Box Series 07: Schools - 1 of 1
Box Series 11: Comic books - 1 of 1
Box Series 12: Calendars and oversized - 1 of 1
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Brooklyn ephemera collection is continually growing and is comprised of a variety of materials donated over the years. Much of its provenance is unknown due to it being a collection of various donations from benefactors both inside and outside the Brooklyn Historical Society.
Separated Materials note
Ephemera related to the Brooklyn Dodgers baseball club has been removed to form the Brooklyn Dodgers collection (ARC.297).
Scope and Contents
The Brooklyn ephemera collection contains materials of mixed provenance accumulated over decades by the Long Island Historical Society (now the Brooklyn Historical Society). The materials relate to a variety of Brooklyn-based institutions and events spanning the period 1814 to 1998. Items include correspondence, announcements, pamphlets, special events programs and notices, note papers, tickets, newspaper clippings, trade cards, advertisements, receipts, invoices, tour maps and information, postcards, and certificates. The collection has been arranged into 12 series:
Business, 1823-1997
Churches, 1857-1997
Civic organizations and celebrations, 1844-1998
Clubs, 1863-1997
Entertainment, 1852-1997
Military, 1852-1965
Schools, 1862-1997
Sports, 1863-1996
Transportation, 1814-1997
Miscellaneous, 1832-1998
Comic books, 1964-1979
Calendars and oversized, 1932-1996
Other Finding Aids note
An earlier version of this finding aid, containing a complete container list, is available in paper form at the Brooklyn Historical Society. Please consult library staff for more information.
Adelphi University.; Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation.; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.). Park Commissioners.; Brooklyn Academy of Music.; Brooklyn Athenaeum.; Brooklyn Chamber of Commerce (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.).; Brooklyn Club (New York, N.Y.).; Brooklyn Cyclones (Baseball team).; Brooklyn Museum.; Brooklyn Philharmonic Symphony Orchestra.; Brooklyn Public Library.; Brooklyn Tabernacle (New York, N.Y.).; Brooklyn Trust Company Building (New York, N.Y.).; Brooklyn Union Gas Company.; Brooklyn-Manhattan Transit Company.; Erasmus Hall High School.; First Presbyterian Church (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.).; Grant, Ulysses S., (Ulysses Simpson), 1822-1885; Historic Districts Council (New York, N.Y.).; Hotel St. George (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.).; National Railway Historical Society.; New York City Transit Authority.; New York Naval Shipyard.; New York Transit Museum.; Pierrepont, John Jay, 1849-1923; St. Francis College (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.).; Visiting Nurse Association of Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.).; Admission tickets; African Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Annual reports; Brochures; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Religious life and customs; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social life and customs; Brooklyn Bridge (New York, N.Y.); Brownstone buildings |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Calendars; Certificates; Clippings (information artifacts); Clubs |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Comic books; Correspondence; Entertainment events |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Invitations; Magazines (periodicals); Menus; Music |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Newsletters; Pamphlets; Popular music |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Printed ephemera; Programs (documents); Prospect Park (New York, N.Y.); Racing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Railroads |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Railroads |z New York (State) |z Long Island; Receipts (financial records); Sports |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Theater |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Trade cards (advertising); United States |x Armed Forces; United States |x History |y Revolution, 1775-1783 |x Centennial celebrations, etc.; Williamsburg Bridge (New York, N.Y.)
- Series 1: Business, 1823-1997
  Scope and Contents
  This series is made up of one document box containing business documents such as checks, receipts, business and trade cards, bank notes, bank statements of condition, and promotional announcements and brochures, as well as a folders on the J.A.R. Elliot Company (makers of Elliot Ear Protectors) and the Hotel St. George. Notable documents include a check signed by Teunis Joralemon in 1823 and a stock certificate from the Joralemon Street Corporation to Maurice Davidson. A securities speculation of Brooklyn Today Inc. is also included.
- Series 2: Churches, 1857-1997
  This series includes issues of the periodical The Parish News, dating between 1905 and 1906, with certain volumes missing, as well as items pertaining to various Brooklyn churches that existed during the early 19th century, such as the Brooklyn Tabernacle, First Presbyterian Church, Saint Barnabas Church, and Saint Michael's Church of Bay Ridge. Tickets, pamphlets, service programs, announcements, miscellaneous flyers, newspaper clippings, and obituaries can be found here.
- Series 3: Civic organizations and celebrations, 1844-1998
  This series contains a variety of materials, including newsletters, special announcements, and invitations, on Brooklyn's early Police Department, Fire Department, and Parks Department. It also covers the Brooklyn Bureau of Community Service, Chamber of Commerce, and Historic Districts Council. Invitations to Fire Department balls and galas can be found, some dating to the 1840s. Other scattered department cards are also present, such as the block watcher card of Warren Zerbe, circa 1973, and the card of Deputy Commissioner Francis L. Dallon of the First Precinct, undated. The Parks folder contains materials relating to Prospect Park, ceremonial dedications, annual reports, tour programs, and invitations. Also included are materials related to specific celebrations such as the Hudson-Fulton celebration of 1909, the Williamsburg Bridge opening of 1903, the Long Island Tercentenary Banquet of 1936, the George Washington Centennial celebration of 1889, and the Bicentennial of 1975 to 1977. The Miscellaneous folder covers local, historical, and ethnic celebrations and includes various tickets, booklets, invitations, promotions, and place cards.
- Series 4: Clubs, 1863-1997
  This series contains two document boxes, with Box 1 containing materials related to Brooklyn club theater programs and Box 2 containing event, menu, and announcement information. Pamphlets, seating lists, donor lists, bulletins, handbooks, and correspondence, all relating to theater programs, can be found in the first box. Box 2 contains event menus by venue, with multiple copies of menus for some events, such as a Lotus Club dinner pamphlet (with menu and speech enclosed) for Dr. St. Clair McKelway, 1906. Box 2 also covers various materials on events or dinners organized by each club, including tickets, invitations, announcements and brochures. Clubs represented include the Apollo Club, City History Club, Elks Club, Hamilton Club, Literary Society Club, Montauk Club, Musical Clubs, Riding and Driving Club, Union Club, and the YMCA/YWCA. Materials on clubs other than those listed above, such as the Rotary Club of Brooklyn and Municipal Club of Brooklyn, are included in the miscellaneous folder in Box 1.
- Series 5: Entertainment, 1852-1997
  This series is comprised of two document boxes that hold theater programs. Box 2 also contains event programs and announcement materials. Theaters are listed alphabetically, and include The Athenaeum, Brooklyn Academy of Music, The Majestic, Montauk Theater, New Brighton Theater, and Payton's Theater, as well as various theaters not documented extensively enough to occupy individual folders, such as the Germania Theater, Brooklyn College Theater, Prospect Hall, and the Carnegie Theater. Each folder contains items such as programs, booklets, and tickets. The Miscellaneous Announcements folder in Box 1 includes a lament for the Brooklyn Theater Fire in 1876. Box 2 contains materials such as musical compositions, Coney Island memorabilia, opera programs, and playbills. A program companion for the weekend festival celebrating the 100th anniversary of Dvorak's New World Symphony and honoring the 50th anniversary of the death of Amy Beach, an American female composer of the late 19th century, is contained in Box 2, Folder 1. The Miscellaneous folder in Box 2 covers various performing arts events, including concerts, musical performances, and plays, organized by music schools, local cultural institutions, and theatres. It includes event calendars, promotions, programs, annual schedules, newspaper clippings, posters, flyers, brochures, and sales guides. It also includes materials on the Brooklyn Center for the Performing Arts and the Public Theater.
- Series 6: Military, 1852-1965
  This series consists of one box with seven folders. Folder topics include regimental receptions, the 23rd Regiment, the Navy and the Brooklyn Navy Yard, memorial services, Memorial Day celebrations, Ulysses S. Grant, and miscellaneous notices, a 1918 World War I Christmas postcard, invitations, and announcements. Included are identification cards, like Frances Haber's Brooklyn Navy Yard I.D. dating from 1943. Other items of interest include tickets and invitations for veterans' events and celebrations. Additionally, publications from the Brooklyn Navy Yard were added to this series from other Brooklyn Navy Yard collections, due to lack of information on donors and dates. They are located in the oversize box as part of Series 12.
- Series 7: Schools, 1862-1997
  This series contains materials relating to schools situated in Brooklyn between 1862 and 1997, such as Brooklyn Central School, Brooklyn Heights Seminary, Erasmus Hall High School, and Packer Institute. Highlights of this series include a booklet memento of the graduating class of 1904 at Packer Institute, tickets and programs of school events, and Erasmus Hall High School's yearbook from 1935. This series also contains information on Erasmus Hall Museum of Education, and Packer Institute's annual reports from 1996 and 1997.
- Series 8: Sports, 1874-2001
  The series contains an assortment of miscellaneous tickets and newspaper clippings of sports-related events from 1874 to 1996. It also contains programs and schedules from the Crescent Football Club (1891-1892), the Brooklyn Prep Midgets' football team (1922), the Brooklyn-Queens Marathon and Indoor Games (1926), the Brooklyn Dodgers Football team (1940), and the Brooklyn Cyclones minor league baseball team (2001, located in Series 12: Oversize box).
  Related Archival Materials note
  Brooklyn Dodgers epehemera has been removed to form the Brooklyn Dodgers collection (ARC.297).
- Series 9: Transportation, 1814-1997
  This series contains materials arranged under the following headings: Trains, The Long Island Railroad, The Brooklyn Elevated Railroad Company, The Brooklyn Union Railroad Company, The Brooklyn Manhattan Transit Company, Subways, Ferries, Union Ferry of New York and Brooklyn Union Ferry, New York City Transit Authority, Bridges, and Miscellaneous. The Miscellaneous folder includes New York Transit Museum records and National Railway Historical Society newsletters. The series also includes one flat box containing 37 mid-20th century subway posters published by the New York City Transit Authority ( The Subway Sun).
  The inclusive dates range from 1814 to 1997. Notable items include identification cards, tickets, and a booklet published by the Institute of Design and Construction warning people of the dangers of building the Verrazano Narrows Bridge and several items related to the opening of the Brooklyn Bridge.
- Series 10: Miscellaneous, 1832-1998
  This series includes a multitude of ephemera relating to various subjects. The following is a general overview of the material formats and subjects represented.
  Fashion clippings in the series are in poor and brittle condition. Photocopies are now in place, in order to preserve the original clippings, in an archival folder behind the rest of the clippings in Folder 3.
  A Political Activity subset contains folders housing materials related to campaign songs, unions, and the Republican Party. Of special interest is American money dating from 1864 and many undated war ration books. An 1860 tune written by John W. Dawson titled "Irrepressible Wide-Awake Campaign Song - The Lost Boy" is also included within the Campaign Songs folder, and the Unions folder contains constitutions and bylaws from various years of the Independent Makers and Machinists Council. It also includes a program for the inauguration ceremony of Brooklyn Borough President Eric L. Adams (2014).
  An Ethnic Groups subset houses materials relevant to African-American, Finish-American and Irish-American affairs.
  A folder titled Stamps is also included and contains a wax seal of Colonel William Smith from 1675 and a 1951 issue of a commemorative stamps booklet on the Battle of Brooklyn.
  The Architecture folder covers historic and landmark buildings in Brooklyn as well as materials on local brownstones, including Wyckoff ancestral house.
  The Art folders house Cultural Council Foundation timesheets and various leaflets and letters about Brooklyn Historical Society exhibitions. They also include exhibitions of various museums and cultural organizations, records of the Brooklyn Arts Council, and events of the Elders Share the Arts.
  The Associations folder covers local and historical societies, containing their newsletters, events, exhibition materials, and invitations. Represented organizations include the Clinton Hill Society, Flatbush Historical Society, Brooklyn Bar Association, Brooklyn Local Economic Development Corporation, Queens Historical Society, Crown Heights Tax Payers and Civic Association, Gravesend Historical Society, Nottingham Association, Society of Old Brooklynites, Hebrew Educational Society, Jack and Jill of America, St. Patrick Society of Brooklyn, Emerald Association, and Society for the Preservation of Weeksville and Bedford-Stuyvesant History.
  The Brownstone Revival movment is represented in the Boerum Hill house tours ephemera folder, containing pamphlets and other items dating from 1966 to 1973.
  The Brooklyn Museum folders cover general information, exhibitions, education, events, and various outreach programs of the museum.
  The Community Development folder includes materials on the Bedford Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation, Forest City Pierrepont Association, Fulton Mall, Atlantic Terminal Brooklyn Center, and Brooklyn Renaissance Plaza, as well as newsletters and annual reports of other corporate bodies.
  The Hospital folder includes records of the Visiting Nurse Association.
  The Library folder includes materials on the Brooklyn Public Library, including annual reports, general information, booklists, exhibition announcements, outreach programs, and event calendars.
  The Miscellaneous folders contain records, newsletters, and magazine articles relating to community affairs and events, historical celebrations, neighborhood tours, gay and lesbian festivals, and not-for-profit organizations.
- Series 11: Comic books, 1964-1979
  This series contains only two comic books. The first comic book dates from 1979 and depicts the cartoon character Bugs Bunny with a Brooklyn accent. The second comic book is of the Flintstone family (from the animated television show The Flintstones) at the World's Fair of 1964 in Flushing, Queens. The Flintstone family was based on the fictional Brooklyn family of the television show The Honeymooners.
- Series 12: Calendars and oversized, 1932-2001
  This series contains calendars relating to Brooklyn life and history and items from Series 1, 6, and 10 that were placed in the oversize box due to their size. Of special note for their photographic retrospectives of Brooklyn are the Brooklyn: Faces and Places calendars of the years 1992 and 1993, This is Brooklyn: The Borough's Historic Districts and Landmarks from 1991, and The Dime Savings Bank of Brooklyn: Through the Eyes of Joseph Pennell, December 1900-1961. This box also contains book covers, a brochure of the South Brooklyn Savings Bank, an advertisement from the New York and New Jersey Port Authority, and a brochure of the Brooklyn Economic Development Corporation. Also included are Brooklyn Navy Yard publications, posters of the Park Slope Artists Open Studio and Brooklyn Botanic Garden, Brooklyn Cyclones items, and a publication on Tribeca West by the Landmarks Preservation Commission.